

Mr. B. Potter

NATIONALITY: British/South African

SUMMARY

Mr. Potter is an independent economist and management consultant. His sector expertise is in extractive industries but he has also worked in manufacturing, financial services, agriculture and infrastructure (particularly power). Previously he was a Senior Associate at Genesis Analytics, a leading emerging markets economic consultancy in Africa, India and the Middle East, where he led their Extractive Industries Advisory Portfolio. He was also the Country Representative in Mozambique, where he was based for four years.

Mr. Potter has led both strategy and operational assignments for private clients such as Anglo American, Unliver, Sasol, Anglo Gold Ashanti and Rio Tinto. He has also consulted extensively in the public and non-profit sector for clients including the World Bank, the Revenue Watch Institute, the FinMark Trust, the UK Department of International Development and GIZ. He has deep experience in coal, platinum, gold, iron ore, steel, natural gas and upsteam oil. He also worked as a Project Manager for AgDevCo, a specialist venture capture organisation investing in African agribusiness startups, and before that he was an Analyst at the Political Risk Division of IHS, where he covered Sub-Saharan economies for clients in the oil, mining, natural gas and power sectors.

Mr. Potter has a particularly interest in the use of risk capital and private equity to promote private sector development in emerging markets, where he has worked with impact investors and mining companies to invest in profitable local SMEs.

He has worked as an economic advisor for both the Mozambican Ministry of Agriculture as well as the Ministry of Planning and Development, where he was an ODI Fellow.

EDUCATION

London School of Economics, 2009, MSc International Political Economy (Distinction) University of Cape Town, 2007, MCom Economics

University of the Witwatersrand, 2006, BCom (Honours) in Economic Science and Business Finance (Distinction)

EMPLOYMENT RECORD

iCOMMIT, Frankfurt/London



July 2013 – present, Co-Founder & CEO

- iCommit is a for-profit digital health startup targeting the US and UK markets using tracking technologies and the principles of behavioral economics to incentivise changes in health behaviours
- Currently in 'beta' stage developing and testing web prototype and applications with early users; building strategic partnerships with insurance companies, employers and commercial agents as distribution channels rolling out both Business-to-Business and Business-to-Consumer business models

INDEPENDENT CONSULTING, Europe/Sub-Saharan Africa

July 2013 – present, **Sub-contracted** to provide:

- Fund design advisory for a \$125M private equity junior mining fund to promote coal and limestone feedstock security for *Eskom*, the public electricity utility in South Africa, with *Vunani Capital Markets* and *Genesis Analytics*
- Supply chain advisory to promote local content in *Sasol's (SPI)* natural gas processing facilities in Mozambique

GENESIS ANALYTICS (Pty) Ltd, Johannesburg

January 2012 – July 2013, Senior Associate

Project management, leadership and teamwork

- Practice Lead for *Extractive Industries Advisory Services* with responsibility for project management, client relationship and budget control of projects
- Project managed large teams of consultants in strategy and operational assignments with major multinational firms in the mining, energy, industrial and manufacturing sectors
- Preparation of a strategic response for *Anglo American* to state intervention in the mining sector enabling the company to diagnose and mitigate risk posed by cost-plus pricing, export supply caps and windfall taxes in the iron ore, steel, platinum and coal sub-sectors
- Provided a business model assessment of the integrated value chain of a NYSE-listed *Energy* and *Chemicals Major* by identifying and unpacking operational disruptions caused by proposed regulatory changes in the production of polymers, chemicals, fertilisers and synthetic fuel resulting in effective company engagement with regulators
- Developed a capital-raising funding strategy for *Anglo Gold Ashanti* to invest \$35M in local SMEs using third party and internal sources; built a financial model based on blended equity, loan and grant instruments which was adopted as a planning tool by the Accounting and Sustainability departments to quantify concessionary finance and trade-offs



- Other projects included the development of procurement toolkits and market demand forecasting models for private
- clients; equity/loan ratio advisory for an industry association' \$30M risk capital Industry-Wide Enterprise Development Fund; and investment pipeline analysis of a \$24M Innovation and Catalytic Grant Facility for the *World Bank* Business development
- Acted as Country Representative (Mozambique) responsible for setting and implementing the company expansion strategy into Mozambique resulting in project origination exceeding the revenue target by 400% and the completion of due diligence to acquire a local company
- Led and authored winning proposals across company practices which resulted in a \$748,000 revenue increase Secondment
- Completed a 6 month secondment to *AgDevCo*, a venture capital organisation, as Project Manager of an investment partnership with *Rio Tinto* and *BP* to promote market opportunities for local entrepreneurs and infrastructure PPPs
- Responsible for oversight of project deliverables and operations including relationship management; investment proposal preparation; due diligence of agribusiness investments; contract brokering between *Rio Tinto* and SMEs; recruitment of staff; and periodic presentation to the Steering Committee where all recommendations were approved and are currently being rolled out in the bankable pre-feasibility stage

THE OVERSEAS DEVELOPMENT INSTITUTE FELLOWSHIP SCHEME, Maputo

October 2009 – September 2011, Economist

Ministry of Planning and Development

- Provided advisory to improve the execution of economic policy in the Mozambican government
- Responsible for investment plan analysis, the development of monitoring indicators; and the preparation of policy
- notes and White Papers covering sectors in infrastructure (power and roads), finance and agriculture
- Led a team of economists researching risk capital approaches to increase lending to SMEs
- Provided advisory and training on the Medium Term Fiscal Framework and Poverty
 Reduction Strategy

Ministry of Agriculture

• Responsible for the oversight of public investments in irrigation, seeds and phyto-sannitory standards; developed a monitoring system to improve the allocation of funding in these sub-



sectors; received and analysed co-funding proposals from private companies; advised on leveraging third-party private capital into existing investments

- Liaised and worked with insurance companies and multilateral agencies to introduce weather-index micro-insurance products in the national market, leading to regulatory approval and the launch of the first product by a local insurer
- Designed and presented a proposal for an irrigation risk capital PPP to the Minister of Agriculture; played a core role in teams writing public sub-sector strategies approved by the National Executive and implemented by the Ministry

CONSULTING ENGAGEMENTS, United Kingdom/South Africa/Mozambique

June 2007 – December 2011, **Contracted** in strategy and economic consulting assignments by:

- *Teal Consulting* and *FSB Impact* to advise *Unilever South Africa* on how to invest in marketing a new product line in a leading FMCG sales portfolio; analysed consumer research data and prepared a strategy to uptrade its consumer base by a 10-14% margin; the recommendations are currently being rolled out in a television advertising campaign
- Norconsult AS to model the impact of a new AC power line on the Mozambican economy
 using project cash flow, capital expenditure and national accounts data in a Computable
 General Equilibrium model that determined the effect of electricity exports on key
 macroeconomic variables (e.g exchange rate) for the end client (a power utility company)
- Exclusive Analysis Ltd, part of the IHS Group (NYSE: IHS), over an 18 month period to provide bespoke reports and forecasts of expropriation, contract and operational risks to investments in 16 African countries including assignments for insurance, banking, private equity, telecommunications, real estate, mining and energy clients
- *DFID*, a United Kingdom government department, in a series of studies providing strategic intervention options on how to work with large extractive companies to promote business linkages with local entrepreneurs in Mozambique resulting in the implementation of an innovative programme with a mining company and an investment organisation
- *GIZ*, a German federal enterprise, to evaluate select SADC country adherence to the Finance and Investment Protocol covering financial integration, stock exchanges, taxation, investment and capital flows
- A major packaging association as a trade analyst working with the Chief Economist over a 2 year period; compiled and collated data into country reports of comparative market access for South Africa and trade competitors in canned consumer products for export markets in the EU, USA, Japan, China, Russia and India; the reports enabled theassociation to successfully lobby for tariff reduction translating into an aggregate sales increase for members



WORLD BANK TRANSPORT FIRM SURVEY, Cape Town

January 2007 – July 2007, Research Assistant

• Conducted interviews with manufacturing firms collecting qualitative and quantitative indicators for a survey on rail, port, road and air cargo bottlenecks in major African logistics hubs

LANGUAGES

- English (native)
- Spanish (fluent Instituto Cervantes DELE Certificate C2 Superior Proficiency Level, engaged to a Spanish national)
- Portuguese (fluent lived and worked in Mozambique for 4 years, translated winning proposals from English to Portuguese)
- German (beginner)